I talk a lot about the power of
taking personal responsibility
for your own health,
for your family’s health.
But there are forces at play when it
comes to influencing what we eat.
Check it out.
"The Role of Marketing and Food Advertisements
in the Obesity Epidemic"
In the 1970s the U.S. government
went from just subsidizing some
of the worst foods to paying
companies to make more of them.
In the 1970’s the farm bills
reversed longstanding policies
aimed at limiting production
to protect prices and instead
started giving payouts in
proportion to output.
Extra calories started pouring
into the food supply.
Then Jack Welch gave a speech.
In 1981, the CEO of General Electric
effectively launched the
“shareholder value movement,”
reorienting the primary
goal of corporations
towards maximizing short-term
returns for investors.
This placed extraordinary pressures
on food companies from Wall Street
to post increasing profit growth every
quarter to boost their share price.
There was already a glut
of calories on the market,
and now they had to sell even more.
This places food and beverage
CEOs in an impossible bind.
It’s not like they’re rubbing
their sticky hands together
at the thought of luring
more Hansels and Gretels
to their doom in their houses of candy.
Food giants couldn’t do
the right thing if they wanted.
They are beholden to investors.
If they stopped marketing to kids,
or tried to sell healthier food, or anything
that could jeopardize their
quarterly profit growth,
Wall Street would demand a
change in management.
Healthy eating is bad for business.
It’s not some grand conspiracy;
it’s not even anyone’s fault, really.
It’s just how the system works.
Given the constant demands for
corporate growth and rapid returns
in an already oversaturated marketplace,
the food industry needed
to get people to eat more.
Like the tobacco industry before
them, they turned to the ad men.
The food industry spends about
$10 billion a year on advertising
and around another $20 billion
on other forms of marketing
such as trade shows, incentives,
consumer promotions,
and supermarket “slotting fees."
Food and beverage companies purchase
shelf space from supermarkets
to prominently display their
most profitable products.
They pay supermarkets.
The practice is also evidently
known as “cliffing,”
because companies are forced to
bid against each other for eye level
shelf placement with the loser
being pushed “over the cliff.”
With slotting fees up to $20,000
per item, per retailer, per city,
you can imagine what kind of
products get the special treatment.
Hint: It ain’t broccoli.
To get a sense of what kind of
products merit prime shelf real estate,
look no further than the checkout aisle.
“Merchandising the power categories
on every lane is critical,”
reads a trade publication
on the “best practices
for superior checkout merchandising.”
They were referring to
candy bars and beverages.
Evidently even a 1 percent
power category boost in sales
could earn a store
an extra $15,000 a year.
It’s not that they necessarily don’t
care about their customers’ health;
publicly traded companies, like most of
the leading grocery store chains,
are said to have a fiduciary duty
to increase profits above
other considerations.
Tens of millions of dollars
are spent annually
advertising a single brand of candy bar.
McDonald’s alone may
spend billions a year.
The food industry now spends
more money on advertising
than any other sector of the economy.
Reagan-era deregulation removed
the limits placed on marketing
food products on television to children.
Now the average child may see
more than 10,000 food ads a year,
and that’s on top of the marketing
online, in print, at school,
on their phones, at the movies,
and everywhere in between.
And nearly all of it for products
detrimental to their health.
Besides the massive early
exposure and ubiquity,
food marketing has become
highly sophisticated.
With the help of child
psychologists, companies learn
how to best influence children
to manipulate their parents.
Packaging is designed to best
attract a child’s attention,
and then placed at their
eye level in the store.
You know those mirrored bubbles
in the ceilings of supermarkets?
They’re not just for shoplifters.
Closed-circuit cameras
and GPS-like devices
on shopping carts are used to
strategize how best to guide shoppers
towards their most profitable products.
Behavioral psychology is widely
applied to increase impulse buying.
Eye movement tracking
technologies are utilized.
The unprecedented rise in the
power, scope, and sophistication
of food marketing starting around 1980,
that aligns well with the blastoff
slope of the obesity epidemic.
Some of the techniques, such as product
placement, in-school advertising,
and event sponsorships skyrocketed
from essentially zero
to multibillion-dollar
industries since the 80s.
This led one economist
to conclude that
“the most compelling single interpretation
of the admittedly incomplete data
we have is that the large increase
in obesity is due to marketing.”
Yes, innovations in manufacturing
and political maneuvering led to a
food supply bursting at the seams with
close to 4,000 calories a day for us all,
but it’s the advances in
marketing manipulations
that are used to try to peddle
that surplus into our mouths.
The opening words of the
Institute of Medicine’s report
on the potential threat
posed by food ads were:
“Marketing works.”
Yeah, there's a large
number of well-conducted
randomized studies I could go through
showing advertising exposure
and how other marketing methods can
change your eating behavior
and get you to eat more, but
what do you need to know beyond
the fact that the industry spends tens
of billions of dollars a year on it.
To get people to drink their
brown sugar water, do you think
Coca-Cola would spend a penny more
than they thought they had to?
It’s like when my medical
colleagues accept “drug lunches”
from pharmaceutical representatives
and take offense
that I would suggest it might
affect their prescribing practices.
Do they really think drug
companies are just in the business
of giving away free money for nothing?
They wouldn’t do it if it didn’t work.
To give you a sense of marketing’s
insidious nature, though,
let me share an interesting
piece of research
published in the world’s
leading scientific journal:
“In-store music affects product
choice” documented an experiment
in which either French accordion
or German Bierkeller music
was played on alternate days in
the wine section of a grocery store.
On the days the French music
was playing in the background
people were three times more
likely to buy French wine,
and on German music days
shoppers were about three times
likely more to buy German wine.
Despite the dramatic effect—
not just a few percent difference
but a complete three-fold reversal—
when approached afterwards,
the vast majority of shoppers denied the
music had any influence on their choice.
We all like to think we
make important life decisions
like what to eat consciously
and rationally.
However, if that were
the case, we wouldn’t be
in the midst of an obesity epidemic.
Most of our day-to-day behavior
does not appear to be dictated
by careful, considered deliberations.
Rather, we tend to make more automatic,
impulsive decisions triggered by
unconscious cues and habitual patterns,
especially when we’re
tired, stressed, or preoccupied.
The unconscious part of
our brain is thought to guide
human behaviors as much
as 95 percent of the time.
This is the arena where marketing
manipulations do their dirty work.
The part of our brain that
governs conscious awareness
may only be able to process about
50 bits of information per second,
which is roughly equivalent
to a short tweet.
Our entire cognitive
capacity, on the other hand,
is estimated to process in excess
of 10 million bits per second.
Because we’re only able to
purposefully process a limited amount
of information at a time,
if we’re distracted or otherwise
unable to concentrate, our decisions
can become even more impulsive.
An elegant illustration of
this “cognitive overload” effect
was provided from an experiment
involving fruit salad and chocolate cake.
Before calls could be made at a touch
of a button or the sound of your voice,
the seven-digit span of
phone numbers was based in part
on the longest sequence most
people can recall on the fly.
We only seem able to hold
about seven chunks of information
(plus or minus two) in our
immediate short-term memory.
OK, so here’s the setup:
randomize people to memorize
either a seven-digit
number or a two-digit number
to be recalled in another
room down the hall.
On the way, offer them the choice of a
fruit salad or a piece of chocolate cake
Memorizing a two-digit number is easy
and presumably takes few
cognitive resources.
Under the two-digit condition,
most chose the fruit salad.
Faced with the same decision,
most of those trying to keep
the seven digits in their
heads just went for the cake.
This can play out in the real world by
potentiating the effect of advertising.
Have people watch a TV show with
commercials for unhealthy snacks
and, no surprise, they eat
more unhealthy snacks,
(compared to those exposed
to non-food ads).
Or maybe that is a surprise.
We all like to think that we’re in
control and not so easily manipulatable.
The kicker, though, is that we
may even be more susceptible
the less we pay attention.
Randomize people to the same two-digit
or seven-digit memorization task
during the show, and the snack
attack effect was magnified
among those who
were more preoccupied.
How many of us have the
TV on in the background or
multi-task during commercial breaks?
This research suggests that it may
make us even more impressionable
to the subversion of our better judgement.
There’s an irony in all this.
Calls for restrictions on
marketing are often resisted
by invoking the banner of freedom.
What does that even mean in this
context, when research shows how
easily our free choices can be
influenced without our conscious control.
A senior policy researcher at
the RAND Corporation even went
as far as to suggest that given
the dire health consequences
of our unhealthy eating habits,
insidious marketing manipulations
“should be considered in
the same light as the invisible
carcinogens and toxins
in the air and water
that can poison us without our awareness.”